{"tossups": [{"question": "A speech to Congress noted \u201cWe owe it [...] to candor and to amicable relations\u201d to engage in this policy. The Russian ukase that asserted sovereignty over present-day Alaska led to the formulation of this policy, which was extended by the Clark Memorandum and Roosevelt Corollary. Secretary of State John Quincy Adams helped draft, for ten points, what 1823 statement of American foreign policy that warned European powers against interfering in the New World, promoted by the fifth U.S. President?", "answer": "<b> Monroe Doctrine</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The perpetrator of this action was represented at his trial by Percy Forman after being captured in London while using the false identity of Ramon Sneyd. The Holy Week Uprising occurred after this event, whose subject was supporting a sanitation strike in Memphis. Robert Kennedy broke news of this event to a crowd in Indianapolis shortly after it occurred at the Lorraine Motel. James Earl Ray perpetrated, for ten points, what event in which the deliverer of the \u201cI Have a Dream\u201d speech died?", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> killing</b>, etc.) of Martin Luther<b> King</b> Jr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "TV shows from this country include<em> Autumn in My Heart</em> and<em> Winter Sonata</em>. This country\u2019s cultural exportation, dubbed the Hallyu, increased upon the release of a video featuring a man who sings on the toilet and pretends to ride a horse as the title \u201cbig brother.\u201d A show set in this country features Hawkeye Pierce, played by Alan Alda, as he worked in a field hospital during a 1950\u2019s war. For ten points, name this setting of the show<em> M*A*S*H</em> and home country of PSY.", "answer": "<b> South Korea</b> (or<b> Republic of Korea</b>; prompt on Korea)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "According to legend, a figure on a quadriga chariot atop this structure had its head turned towards the French Consulate when it was returned after the Napoleonic Wars. At this location, Leonard Bernstein conducted a rendition of Beethoven\u2019s Ninth Symphony with the word \u201cjoy\u201d replaced with \u201cfreedom.\u201dRonald Reagan gave a speech in front of this location that demanded that, if Gorbachev sought peace, he should \u201ccome here to this gate\u201d. For ten points, name this triumphal arch that formed part of the border between West and East Berlin.", "answer": "<b> Brandenburg</b> Gate (or<b> Brandenburg</b>er Tor)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Benoit Peeters wrote about \u201cthe world\u201d of this author. This man wrote the series<em> Quick & Flupke</em>, and his work was influenced by his friend Zhang Chongren. Many of this man\u2019s works appeared in<em> Le</em> <em>Petit Vingti`eme</em>. This man pioneered the \u201cligne claire\u201d drawing style. This man\u2019s most famous character made his debut \u201cin the Land of the Soviets\u201d with his dog Snowy. For ten points, name this Belgian author who created the characters Captain Haddock and Tintin.", "answer": "<b> Herg\u00b4e</b> (or Georges Prosper<b> Remi</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "A campaign pin that opposed this man said that this man wasn\u2019t \u201ceven a good banana.\u201d In a debate, this man claimed that \u201cDemocrat wars\u201d in the 20th century killed as many people as the population of Detroit. In one election, this man ran with former professional football player Jack Kemp. After Nelson Rockefeller declined to run for the vice presidency, this man was chosen to replace him for the Election of 1976. For ten points, name this running mate of Gerald Ford and opponent of Bill Clinton in the election of 1996.", "answer": "Robert \u201cBob\u201d<b> Dole</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man dueled Humphrey Marshall over a bill regulating suit cloths. This man was sued by his slave, Charlotte Dupuy, for her freedom, though he also helped found the colony of Liberia as president of the American Colonization Society. This man used the 36-30 line as a basis for determining the legality of slavery within a state in his Missouri Compromise. This proponent of the American System was accused of arranging a \u201cCorrupt Bargain\u201d with John Quincy Adams. For ten points, name this \u201cGreat Compromiser\u201dfrom Kentucky.", "answer": "Henry<b> Clay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man successfully defeated an ambush at the Battle of the Boarn, killing the Frisian king Poppo. In one battle, this man sent scouts to free prisoners from the enemy camp, leading to a full-scale retreat by the enemy, believing their plunder was being stolen. After Odo of Aquitaine was defeated at the Battle of the Garonne River, he requested military aid from this man. In his most famous victory, this man used infantry squares to repel repeated cavalry charges ordered by Abd al-Rahman, stopping the Umayyad advance into Europe. For ten points, name this Frankish leader who won the Battle of Tours.", "answer": "<b> Charles Martel</b> (or<b> Charles the Hammer</b>; prompt on Charles)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In a speech referencing this policy, its formulator said he would \u201cdedicate the nation\u201d to someone who\u201crespects himself and, because he does so, respects the rights of others.\u201d As part of this policy, the film <em>Saludos Amigos</em> was shown in numerous countries. The implementation of this policy caused US Marines to withdrawal from Nicaragua. In support of this policy, Cordell Hull stated \u201cNo country has the right to intervene in the internal or external affairs of another.\u201d The Roosevelt Corollary was amended by, for ten points, what policy of nonintervention in Latin America?", "answer": "<b> Good Neighbor</b> Policy", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Simba uprising in this country ended with foreign intervention during Operation Dragon Rouge. Pierre Mulele was dismembered after being offered amnesty in this country. Moise Tshombe failed to organize elections in this country following the overthrow of Joseph Kasavubu. A \u201cPeople\u2019s Republic\u201d in this country was proclaimed at Stanleyville. Patrice Lumumba was killed in this country by Katangese troops. For ten points, name this African country formerly called Zaire.", "answer": "<b> Democratic Republic of the Congo</b> (or<b> DRC</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Abd al-Rahim al-Nashiri, a member of this group, was waterboarded at Guantanamo Bay; al-Nashiri is alleged to have planned this group\u2019s attack on a missile destroyer in the port of Aden. Operation Infinite Reach was launched in response to this organization\u2019s August 1998 attacks on American embassies in Tanzania and Kenya. The USS<em> Cole</em> bombing was planned by, for ten points, what terrorist group, led by Osama bin Laden, that carried out the 9/11 attacks?", "answer": "<b> al-Qaeda</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One of these speeches notes that \u201cthere can be no era of good feeling save among men of good will,\u201d while another includes the observation of \u201cone-third of a nation ill housed, ill</b> <b>clad, ill nourished.\u201d The (+)</b> <b>last of these orations began with the claim that \u201cI know it</b> <b>is America\u2019s purpose that we shall not fail.\u201d One of these orations notes that \u201cthe money lenders have fled from their high places\u201d and began with the assertion that \u201cthe (*) </b> only thing we have to fear is fear itself.\u201d For ten points, name these orations given by a four-term president each time he was elected.", "answer": "<b> inaugural</b> addresses by<b> F</b>ranklin<b> Roosevelt</b> (or<b> inaugurals of FDR</b>; prompt on partial answers; do not accept fireside chats)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This campaign\u2019s aftermath included the rise of brigandage in a certain region, which was combated with the Legge Pica law. During this campaign, peasants in the city of Bronte revolted but were put down by forces under Nino (+) Bixio. The victorious commander of this campaign gave up his territorial gains with the \u201chandshake of Teano.\u201d After landing at Marsala, the eventual victorious force in this campaign won its first battle at Calatafimi. After the decisive Battle of the (*)</b> Volturnus in this campaign, Bourbon king Francis II relinquished his throne. For ten points, name this campaign in which forces under Giuseppe Garibaldi conquered the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies, named for the number of men in the expedition force.", "answer": "<b> Expedition of the Thousand</b> (or<b> Spedizione dei Mille</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "He served as the successor</b> <b>to (+)</b> <b>Smenkhare. Both Horemheb and the Vizier Ay advised this ruler, who moved the</b> <b>capital back to Thebes. Under the reign of this ruler, (*)</b> Amun was restored to his position of chief god, replacing Aten. Lord Carvanon was allegedly cursed by his discovery of this ruler\u2019s tomb in the Valley of the Kings. For ten points, name this Egyptian pharaoh and son of Akhenaten who died in his teenage years.", "answer": "King<b> Tut</b>ankhamun (or<b> Tut</b>ankhaten)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This artist painted a firing squad of soldiers walking away from a man dressed in black lying facedown on the ground in</b><em><b> The Death of Marshal Ney</b></em><b>. Another of his works shows the Roman (+) emperor observing the central action from his box above a red tapestry with a vulture on it, while a line of Vestal Virgins signals the murmillo to not spare the retiarius with a (*)</b> thumbs-down gesture. For ten points, name this prominent French painter of academic art, best known for depicting a gladiator about to kill his vanquished opponent in<em> Pollice Verso</em>.", "answer": "Jean-Leon<b> Gerome</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>After this group demanded that free groceries be distributed to the homeless, Ronald Reagan joked that he hoped the food would be tainted by botulism. Colston Westbrook</b> <b>invited this group\u2019s founder, Donald DeFreeze, who later took the name (+)</b> <b>\u201cCinque,\u201d to</b> <b>join the Black Cultural Association in a Vacaville prison. One member of this group with the pseudonym \u201cTania\u201d was captured by a security camera yelling at (*) </b> bank customers during this group\u2019s robbery of the Hibernia Bank; that member was earlier abducted from her Berkeley apartment in 1974. For ten points, name this radical group that kidnapped Patty Hearst.", "answer": "<b> S</b>ymbionese<b> L</b>iberation<b> A</b>rmy", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The</b><em><b> sagitta</b></em><b> ship was used to quickly traverse between this body of water and rivers by pirates in Omis. This body of water was home to pirates called Uskoks, who were brutally</b> <b>suppressed during the lead-up to the Thirty Years\u2019 War in the War of (+)</b> <b>Gradisca.</b> <b>The</b><em><b> lembus</b></em><b> was a particularly fast ship used by pirates in this body of water, which was effectively controlled by the Narentine kingdom during the 7th to 9th centuries. A queen of the (*)</b> Ardiaeans called Teuta was notorious for encouraging piracy in this body of water, which led to Rome invading and destroying the Ardiaean kingdom in the Illyrian Wars. For ten points, name this sea often terrorized by pirates who raided Venetian ships.", "answer": "<b> Adriatic</b> Sea", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>It is not related to Scottish independence, but one member of this organization joined only after negotiating the Edinburgh Agreement. At least eight members of this organization</b> <b>can engage in \u201cenhanced cooperation\u201d thanks to its Treaty of (+)</b> <b>Nice. It created a set</b> <b>of \u201cconvergence criteria,\u201d which included the absence of \u201cexcessive deficit,\u201d to determine whether its members could use its (*) </b> common currency. This organization was created by the 1993 Treaty of Maastricht. For ten points, name this international organization that has not yet admitted Turkey as a member.", "answer": "<b> European Union</b> (or<b> EU</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>At this event, a man tried to clarify his quote about leaping into his grave laughing at the thought of killing people. Gideon Hausner gave many emotional speeches at this event,</b> <b>which William Buckley claimed was part of an overall (+)</b> <b>\u201crefusal to forgive.\u201d This event</b> <b>came about after Peter Malkin and confederates captured a man living on Garibaldi Street in (*)</b> Buenos Aires. During it, a man sitting inside a bulletproof glass booth explained that he felt no guilt for his actions. The phrase \u201cbanality of evil\u201d appeared in a book about this event by Hannah Arendt. For ten points, name this 1960s trial in Israel of a high-ranking Nazi.", "answer": "the<b> trial</b> of Adolf<b> Eichmann</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man killed William Heselrig during the Action at Lanark. Blind Harry wrote</b> <b>an epic poem about this man. This man resigned as Guardian after his defeat at the</b> <b>Battle of Falkirk. This man surrendered to King Edward I at (+)</b> <b>Robroyston and</b> <b>was executed shortly afterwards. This man\u2019s forces joined Andrew Moray\u2019s forces to</b> <b>gain victory at the Battle of (*)</b> Stirling Bridge. For ten points, name this Scottish hero, the subject of the film<em> Braveheart</em>.", "answer": "William<b> Wallace</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}